[
  {
    "number": 1,
    "question": "A demand schedule is",
    "options": [
      "A table showing the relationship between price and quantity demanded of a commodity",
      "A table showing the price of goods",
      "The quantity of goods the consumer is prepared to buy",
      "A table showing the consumer demand in order of importance"
    ],
    "answer": "A table showing the relationship between price and quantity demanded of a commodity"
  },
  {
    "number": 2,
    "question": "The resources used in production are called",
    "options": [
      "variable inputs",
      "factors of production",
      "capital for production",
      "fixed inputs"
    ],
    "answer": "factors of production"
  },
  {
    "number": 3,
    "question": "The factor of production which takes the initiative in combining resources for production is known as",
    "options": [
      "capital",
      "land",
      "labour",
      "entrepreneur"
    ],
    "answer": "entrepreneur"
  },
  {
    "number": 4,
    "question": "The main objective of setting up a private business organization is to",
    "options": [
      "Protect the interest of the owners",
      "Promote exports",
      "Provide infrastructure",
      "Maximize profit"
    ],
    "answer": "Maximize profit"
  },
  {
    "number": 5,
    "question": "The transfer of ownership of a public enterprise to individuals and firms is called",
    "options": [
      "Commercialization",
      "Nationalization",
      "Privatization",
      "Restructuring"
    ],
    "answer": "Privatization"
  },
  {
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Economic problems arise mainly as a result of",
    "options": [
      "Lack of foresight on the part of resource users",
      "Limitations in availability of resources",
      "Excessive wastage of available resources",
      "Inaccurate statistical data in West Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "Limitations in availability of resources"
  },
  {
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Which of the following is central to the definition of economics",
    "options": [
      "resources",
      "wants",
      "scarcity",
      "capital"
    ],
    "answer": "scarcity"
  },
  {
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Limited liability means that",
    "options": [
      "The debts of a company can only be paid from its own assets",
      "The debts of a company are paid from business as well as private funds of the owners",
      "A company does not have to pay its debts",
      "The debts of company must be paid from private funds only"
    ],
    "answer": "The debts of a company are paid from business as well as private funds of the owners"
  },
  {
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Which of the following sectors of the economy is estimated to be the largest employer of labour in the country?",
    "options": [
      "Agriculture",
      "Distribution",
      "Mining and petroleum",
      "Construction"
    ],
    "answer": "Agriculture"
  },
  {
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Factors that determine the size of a firm are as follows except",
    "options": [
      "Total assets",
      "Number of employees",
      "Name of the firm",
      "Volume of the output"
    ],
    "answer": "Name of the firm"
  },
  {
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Wants as opposed to demands",
    "options": [
      "Depends on the price",
      "Are the goods the consumer plans to acquire",
      "Are the unlimited desires of the consumer",
      "Are the goods the consumer has acquired"
    ],
    "answer": "Are the unlimited desires of the consumer"
  },
  {
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Who saw Economics as an inquiry into the nature and causes of the wealth of nations?",
    "options": [
      "Adam Smith",
      "Alfred Marshal",
      "A.C. Pigou",
      "Davenport"
    ],
    "answer": "A.C. Pigou"
  },
  {
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Production is completed when",
    "options": [
      "raw materials are converted into finished goods",
      "goods reach the final consumer",
      "goods are taken to the warehouse",
      "when utility is added"
    ],
    "answer": "goods reach the final consumer"
  },
  {
    "number": 14,
    "question": "The reward accrued to capital in production is",
    "options": [
      "Interest",
      "Wages",
      "Salary",
      "Profit"
    ],
    "answer": "Interest"
  },
  {
    "number": 15,
    "question": "The following factors affect demand except",
    "options": [
      "Income",
      "other prices",
      "Habit",
      "Inferiority"
    ],
    "answer": "Inferiority"
  },
  {
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Economics as a field of study is a",
    "options": [
      "Social science",
      "Pure science",
      "Political science",
      "Physical science"
    ],
    "answer": "Social science"
  },
  {
    "number": 17,
    "question": "If a student decides to buy rice instead of beans, which of the following principle is applicable?",
    "options": [
      "Choice",
      "Opportunity cost",
      "Scale of preference",
      "Exchange"
    ],
    "answer": "Choice"
  },
  {
    "number": 18,
    "question": "One of the following are noticeable similarity between economics and physics",
    "options": [
      "Demand",
      "Generalizations",
      "Graph",
      "Choice"
    ],
    "answer": "Graph"
  },
  {
    "number": 19,
    "question": "The study of Economics becomes necessary because of the",
    "options": [
      "Large population size of the world",
      "Scarcity of resources",
      "Opportunity cost of goods and services",
      "Need to satisfy every desire of man"
    ],
    "answer": "Scarcity of resources"
  },
  {
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Scale of preference shows",
    "options": [
      "Income of consumers in order of size",
      "Utilities enjoyed by consumers",
      "Opportunity cost of goods consumed",
      "Consumers' wants in order of priority"
    ],
    "answer": "Consumers' wants in order of priority"
  },
  {
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Economics is often described as a science because it",
    "options": [
      "Adopts the use of laboratory experiments",
      "Involves accurate prediction of human beings",
      "Makes use of controlled experiments",
      "Uses scientific methods to explain observed phenomena"
    ],
    "answer": "Uses scientific methods to explain observed phenomena"
  },
  {
    "number": 22,
    "question": "The foregone alternative in Economics is simply the",
    "options": [
      "Marginal cost",
      "Cost of a foregone product",
      "Total cost",
      "Opportunity cost"
    ],
    "answer": "Opportunity cost"
  },
  {
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Economic problems arise mainly as a result of",
    "options": [
      "Inaccurate statistical data in West Africa",
      "Excessive wastage of available resources",
      "Lack of foresight on the part of resource users",
      "Limitations in availability of resources"
    ],
    "answer": "Limitations in availability of resources"
  },
  {
    "number": 24,
    "question": "The decision on what to produce is a problem in",
    "options": [
      "All economic systems",
      "A mixed economic system only",
      "A democratic socialist economy only",
      "A free enterprise system only"
    ],
    "answer": "All economic systems"
  },
  {
    "number": 25,
    "question": "An arrangement of data in rows and columns is referred to as a",
    "options": [
      "Graph",
      "Bar chart",
      "Pie chart",
      "Table"
    ],
    "answer": "Table"
  },
  {
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Which of the following best describes the mode?",
    "options": [
      "Observation with highest frequency",
      "Average of two middle numbers",
      "Item that occupies the middle position",
      "Difference of two extreme values"
    ],
    "answer": "Observation with highest frequency"
  },
  {
    "number": 27,
    "question": "The movement along the same demand curve is a",
    "options": [
      "Change in demand",
      "Change in quantity demanded",
      "Shift in demand",
      "Market demand"
    ],
    "answer": "Change in quantity demanded"
  },
  {
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Giffen commodities are those commodities",
    "options": [
      "Which give rise to a cobweb situation",
      "For which demand increases as price increases",
      "Which have a low price elasticity of demand",
      "Which are in short supply"
    ],
    "answer": "For which demand increases as price increases"
  },
  {
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Which of the following is a luxury item?",
    "options": [
      "Petrol",
      "Textbook",
      "Pencil",
      "Gold"
    ],
    "answer": "Gold"
  },
  {
    "number": 30,
    "question": "If the demand function is Qd = -0.5p + 20. Calculate the quantity demanded when price is $15.00.",
    "options": [
      "-$27.50",
      "-$12.50",
      "$12.50",
      "$27.50"
    ],
    "answer": "$12.50"
  },
  {
    "number": 31,
    "question": "There is unemployment of resources when production is",
    "options": [
      "Within the production possibility curve",
      "Outside the production possibility curve",
      "Along the production possibility curve",
      "Adequate to meet market demand"
    ],
    "answer": "Within the production possibility curve"
  },
  {
    "number": 32,
    "question": "Increase in supply of a product can be caused by",
    "options": [
      "Change in taste and fashion of consumers",
      "Increase in the incomes of consumers",
      "A fall in the cost of production",
      "Increase in the price of a product"
    ],
    "answer": "A fall in the cost of production"
  },
  {
    "number": 33,
    "question": "Supply in economics means making",
    "options": [
      "Goods and services available to consumers",
      "Goods available to the market at a given price and at a given period",
      "Available the goods and services which consumers require",
      "Only goods which are available to consumers"
    ],
    "answer": "Goods available to the market at a given price and at a given period"
  },
  {
    "number": 34,
    "question": "Goods which have to be paid for are known as",
    "options": [
      "Physical goods",
      "Economic goods",
      "Free goods",
      "Intangible goods"
    ],
    "answer": "Economic goods"
  },
  {
    "number": 35,
    "question": "Warehousing is an economic activity that falls under",
    "options": [
      "Tertiary production",
      "Intermediate production",
      "Secondary production",
      "Primary production"
    ],
    "answer": "Tertiary production"
  },
  {
    "number": 36,
    "question": "The demand for labour is",
    "options": [
      "Composite demand",
      "Derived demand",
      "Joint demand",
      "Competitive demand"
    ],
    "answer": "Derived demand"
  },
  {
    "number": 37,
    "question": "The money payment made to owners of land and labour are",
    "options": [
      "Rent and wages",
      "Interest and profit",
      "Wages and interest",
      "Dividends and salary"
    ],
    "answer": "Rent and wages"
  },
  {
    "number": 38,
    "question": "Human development can be improved if",
    "options": [
      "Banks give more loans to businessmen",
      "Large family sizes are encouraged",
      "General education and training is encouraged",
      "It is handled by the private sector only"
    ],
    "answer": "General education and training is encouraged"
  },
  {
    "number": 39,
    "question": "Capital as a factor of production is important because",
    "options": [
      "It enables us to carry out tasks which cannot be done by human effort only",
      "Most tasks can be done with bare hands",
      "People can work without capital",
      "It provides money which is essential for the growth of business"
    ],
    "answer": "It provides money which is essential for the growth of business"
  },
  {
    "number": 40,
    "question": "One important feature of sole proprietorship is that",
    "options": [
      "It is limited liability business",
      "The business is owned by shareholders",
      "One person bears all the risk",
      "It is a legal entity"
    ],
    "answer": "One person bears all the risk"
  },
  {
    "number": 41,
    "question": "A business outfit is said to be a public limited company when it",
    "options": [
      "Is owned by government",
      "Operated as a public corporation",
      "Is run by the public",
      "Sells its shares to members of the public"
    ],
    "answer": "Sells its shares to members of the public"
  },
  {
    "number": 42,
    "question": "Which of the following features distinguishes a public limited company from a private limited company?",
    "options": [
      "Perpetual existence",
      "Limited liability",
      "Legal entity",
      "Sale of shares to the public"
    ],
    "answer": "Sale of shares to the public"
  },
  {
    "number": 43,
    "question": "The movement of labour from one grade to one entirely different grade is an example of",
    "options": [
      "Industrial labour mobility",
      "Horizontal occupational mobility",
      "Vertical occupational mobility",
      "Geographical mobility"
    ],
    "answer": "Horizontal occupational mobility"
  },
  {
    "number": 44,
    "question": "When a worker changes from one type of job to another it is called",
    "options": [
      "Geographical mobility of labour",
      "Occupational mobility of labour",
      "Immobility of labour",
      "Rural-urban migration"
    ],
    "answer": "Occupational mobility of labour"
  },
  {
    "number": 45,
    "question": "Subsistence farming means producing food",
    "options": [
      "Mainly for the need of an immediate and extended family",
      "Crops for sale mainly",
      "Crops mainly for export",
      "To feed the community around"
    ],
    "answer": "Mainly for the need of an immediate and extended family"
  },
  {
    "number": 46,
    "question": "The central bank controls money supply through all the following except",
    "options": [
      "Lending to the public",
      "Bank rate",
      "Legal reserve requirements",
      "Open market operations"
    ],
    "answer": "Lending to the public"
  },
  {
    "number": 47,
    "question": "Which of the following financial institutions was originally known as a building society?",
    "options": [
      "Development bank",
      "Insurance company",
      "Mortgage bank",
      "Merchant bank"
    ],
    "answer": "Mortgage bank"
  },
  {
    "number": 48,
    "question": "Banks create money by",
    "options": [
      "Giving drafts to customers",
      "Printing more money",
      "Lending out deposit to borrowers",
      "Issuing cheques"
    ],
    "answer": "Lending out deposit to borrowers"
  },
  {
    "number": 49,
    "question": "What happens when the central bank increases the bank rate?",
    "options": [
      "Amount of borrowing increases",
      "Amount of borrowing decreases",
      "Supply of money increases",
      "Commercial banks are not affected"
    ],
    "answer": "Amount of borrowing decreases"
  },
  {
    "number": 50,
    "question": "Middlemen in an economy perform the function of",
    "options": [
      "Distribution",
      "Exchange",
      "Production",
      "Consumption"
    ],
    "answer": "Distribution"
  }
]
